A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Governance and Public Policy (GPP), Department Chronological Correspondence Files FA1550
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Governance and Public Policy (GPP), Department Chronological Correspondence Files
1991-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1550
1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as part of Accession 2019:090 Ford Foundation records, Staff Subject Files, Jan Jaffe.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of two series. Files in Series 1 were arranged in order to restore the intended chronological organization.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Chronological files, 1991-1995
Series 2. Log files, 1993
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation's Governance and Public Policy Program (GPP) operated during the early to mid-1990s. It oversaw grants for programs and projects involved with citizen participation and electoral politics, policy think tanks and interdisciplinary approaches to economic and social policy, improving state and local government, increasing the number of minorities in the public policy field, and philanthropy and the nonprofit sector. GPP grantees included the Woodrow Wilson Program, the Innovations in American Government Awards Program, and the Public Agenda Foundation among many others.
Jan Jaffe served as Acting Director for the program during a transition period between 1992 and 1993. June Zeitlin then became Director in 1993 and continued to lead the program when it transitioned to become the Governance and Civil Society Program in 1996.
Ford Foundation GPP staff members included:
Jan Jaffe - Acting Director
June Zeitlin - Director
Maria Buck - Program Assistant
Emmett Carson - Program Officer
William Diaz - Program Officer
Maxine Gaddis - Assistant Grants Administrator
Lance Lindblom - Program Officer
Michael Lipsky - Program Officer
Lori Matia - Grants Administrator
Michael Seltzer - Program Officer
Marcia Smith - Program Officer
Ivy Steber - Assistant Grants Administrator
Ford Foundation; Economic policy; Local government; Politics, Practical; Public policy; Research institutes; Social policy; Work and family
- Chronological files, 1991-1995; 1; 1.14 Cubic Feet About 3 LTR size document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the chronological files of the Ford Foundation's Governance and Public Program Policy (GPP) staff members. The first file in the series contains the correspondence of Jan Jaffe who served as Acting Director of GPP between 1992 and 1993. The correspondence in this file is arranged alphabetically by the name of the correspondent organization or individual. The rest of the files in the series contain the correspondence of multiple GPP staff members. Documents in these files are organized by creator.
  Jan Jaffe became GPP Director in 1993. Her correspondence as well as that of Emmett Carson, William Diaz, Maxine Gaddis, Lance Lindblom, Lori Matia, Michael Seltzer, Marcia Smith, and Ivy Steber are contained within the files. The GPP department correspondence documents the program's support of initiatives and projects involved with citizen participation and electoral politics, policy think tanks and interdisciplinary approaches to economic and social policy, improving state and local government, increasing the number of minorities in the public policy field, and philanthropy and the nonprofit sector. There is a significant amount of material within the collection that regards the program's support for the Innovations in American Government Awards as well as the Woodrow Wilson Program. Some correspondence also documents the GPP staff members' involvement with the Ford Foundation's women and gender equity related projects such as the Work-Family Collaborative Action Research Project. The correspondence of Grants Administrators, Lori Matia, Maxine Gaddis, and Ivy Steber, generally concerns grants approvals and reminders for narrative and financial report submissions.
  - Jan Jaffe chronological file, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Chronological file, 1993 June-July (Box 1, Folder 4)
    File subheadings include:
    Carson, Emmett
    Diaz, William
    Lipsky, Michael
    Jaffe, Jan
    Matia, Lori
    Steber, Ivy
  - Chronological file, 1993 November-December (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Zeitlin, June
  - Chronological file, 1993 December (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Chronological file, 1994 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chronological file, 1994 February (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Chronological file, 1994 March (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chronological file, 1994 April (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chronological file, 1994 July (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Smith, Marcia
  - Chronological file, 1994 August (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Chronological file, 1994 August-October (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Chronological file, 1995 January-February (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Chronological file, 1995 March (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Chronological file, 1995 April (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Gaddis, Maxine
  - Chronological file, 1995 May (Box 3, Folder 18-19)
    Seltzer, Michael
  - Chronological file, 1995 June-July (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Chronological file, 1995 July-September (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
    Lindblom, Lance
- Log files, 1993; 2; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  - Logs, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Series contains one file of Ford Foundation Governance and Public Policy Program (GPP) grant request logs. Log records document requests made by organizations for Foundation grant support.